# Anand Mudgerikar

3685 De Soto Drive, West Lafayette, IN | 765-714-2796 amudgeri@purdue.edu | Website | Linkedin | Google Scholar

#### Research Interest

My research interests lie in Information Security, Cryptography, Computer Networks and Machine Learning. My research aim is to combine machine learning techniques, like reinforcement learning, with security techniques like intrusion detection to achieve stronger protection of computer systems and networks, while at the same time optimizing network functionality requirements, such as QoS in SDN enabled networks.

## **EDUCATION**

Purdue University PhD in Computer Science, Advisor: Elisa Bertino	West Lafayette, IN  Jan 2016 – Present
Purdue University  Masters in Information Security (CERIAS)	West Lafayette, IN Jan 2015 – May 2016
DA-IICT Bachelor of Technology in Information and Communication Technology	Gandhinagar, India Aug. 2009 – May 2013

## EXPERIENCE

#### Graduate Research Assistant

Jan 2016 – Present

Purdue University, Advisor: Dr. Elisa Bertino

West Lafayette, IN

- Research projects on machine-learning techniques for security and safety of IoT device systems and for security of Computer Networks.
  - \* Jarvis: Developed a constrained reinforcement learning framework for optimizing user QoS requirements and network functionalities in IoT and SDN environments (ICDCS 2020).
  - \* Developed a novel approach for optimizing RL based distributed analytics in coalition environments using GAN based domain adaptation developed as part of the **IBM DAIS Project**.
  - \* Kalis: Developed a self-adapting, knowledge-driven expert Intrusion Detection System able to detect attacks in real time across a wide range of IoT systems (ICDCS 2017).
  - \* **Heimdall:** Developed a whitelist-based anomaly detection technique tailored towards IoT devices in order to detect DDoS attacks (**IEEE IoT Journal 2017**).
- Research projects on techniques for protection against cryptographic ransomware.
  - \* **RW-Guard:** Designed a Systematic Approach for Cryptographic Ransomware Detection using anomaly detection, decoys and hooking techniques in Windows systems (**RAID 2020**).
- Research projects on hardware-accelerated cryptographic authentication
  - \* Developed a new suite of cryptographic mechanisms (MILCOMM 2015) as part of my masters thesis, employing hardware-acceleration using GPUs to ensure secure and reliable operation in IoVs(Internet of Vehicles) .
  - \* Provisional Patent filled by Purdue University: **Hardware Accelerated Priority Based Message**Authentication for Vehicular Networks

### Security Research Intern

May 2017 - Dec 2018

HPE Labs, Advisor: Dr. Puneet Sharma

Palo Alto, CA

- E-Spion: Developed a system level anomaly based Intrusion Detection system on the edge which profiles IoT device behaviors (Asia CCS 2019).
- Patent filled by HPE: Detecting attacks on computing devices, US20190238567A1
- Dito IoT HoneyPot: Developed a high interaction 'best effort' honey pot system which replicates IoT devices on the network.
- Runners up in HPE internship projects fair 2017 and presented at (HPE TechCon 2017).

## Security Architecture Intern

May 2016 – Aug 2016

IBM Research, Advisor: Dr. Ashish Kundu

Yorktown Heights, NY

• Worked on designing and implementing the Single sign-on (SSO) security architecture for the educational platform of IBM Watson.

July 2013 – Nov 2014

TIFAC, DST Govt. of India

New Delhi, India

- Conducted a research study to analyze the security threats in 3rd party applications and responsible for ensuring network security to prevent any unauthorized access.
- Worked on improving the IPSec standard by incorporating secure Multicast functionality using multi-party key computation.

## Graduate Teaching Assistant

Jan 2016 - Dec 2016

Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN

• Worked as a teaching assistant for courses CS240: Programming in C and CS381: Introduction to Analysis of Algorithms.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Mudgerikar A. and Bertino E., Jarvis: Moving towards a smarter IoT using RL, ICDCS 2020 Mudgerikar A., Sharma P. and Bertino E., Edge based Intrusion Detection for the Internet Of Things, ACM Transactions on Management Information Systems, 'Special Issue on Analytics for Cybersecurity and Privacy', 2020.

Mudgerikar A., Sharma P. and Bertino E., E-Spion: System Level Intrusion Detection for the Internet Of Things, AsiaCCS 2019.

Mehnaz S., Mudgerikar A. and Bertino E., RWGuard: An Approach for Detection and Recovery of Cryptographic RansomWare, RAID 2018, pp. 114-136.

Midi D., Mudgerikar A., Rullo N. and Bertino E., Kalis - A System for Knowledge-driven Adaptable Intrusion Detection for the Internet of Things, ICDCS 2017

Yavuz A., Mudgerikar A., Singla A., I. Papapanagiotou and Bertino E., Real-Time Digital Signatures for Time-Critical Networks IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security 2017

Midi D., Habibi J., Mudgerikar A. and Bertino E., Heimdall: Mitigating the Internet of Insecure Things, IEEE Internet of Things Journal 2017

Singla A., Mudgerikar A., Papapanagiotou I. and Yavuz A., HAA: Hardware-Accelerated Authentication for Internet of Things in Mission Critical Vehicular Networks, MILCOMM 2015 Mudgerikar A. and Das M.L., Secure multicast using IPsec and multi-party key computation, Int. J. Internet Technology and Secured Transactions, Inderscience Publications, Vol. 5, No. 2, pp.149-162.

#### Patents

Patent Disclosure, **Detecting attacks on computing devices**, US20190238567A1 Patent Disclosure, **Hardware Accelerated Priority Based Message Authentication for Vehicular Networks**, OTC:2015-PAPA-67164

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: C++, C, Java, Python, PHP, SQL, JavaScript, Android Development, CUDA.

Security: Network Intrusion Detection, Malware Analysis, Cryptography

Tools: Wireshark, Nmap, OpenVAS, Nessus, MetaSploit, Ollydgb, Kali Linux, Android Reverse Engineering.

Machine Learning: Reinforcement Learning, System Modelling

Tools: OpenAI gym, NumPy, Pandas, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn, Keras

**General**: OpenFlow, openSSL, ns2, SmartThings, IFTTT, Vim, Git, VirtualBox, Django Framework, MATLAB, MySQL, Latex.

## Interests

Brazilian Jiu Jitsu, Table Tennis, Soccer, Cricket, Dota 2

College Representative (DA-IICT), IN-CTF and member of B01lers CTF Group, Purdue.

Captain of College Table Tennis Team, DA-IICT, India (2009-2013)

Coordinator of BattleDrome, LAN Gaming event in DA-IICT's Techno-Cultural festival, India